[Music]
Reedman reads The Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
12 "You slept soundly, Jonas?" his mother asked at the morning meal. "No
dreams Jonah simply smiled and nodded, not ready to lie, not willing to tell the
truth. "I slept very soundly," he said. "I wish this one would," his father
said, leaning down from his chair to touch Gabriel's waving fist. The basket
was on the floor beside him; in its corner, beside Gabriel's head, the stuffed
hippo sat staring with its blank eyes. "So do I," Mother said, rolling her
eyes. "He's so fretful at night." Jonas had not heard the new child
during the night because as always, he had slept soundly. But it was not true that he had
no dreams. Again and again, as he slept, he had slid down that snow covered hill.
Always, in the dream seemed as if there were a destination: a something —he could not
grasp what— —that lay beyond the place where the thickness of snow brought the sled to a
stop. He was left, upon awakening, with the feeling that he wanted, even been somehow
needed, to reach the something that waited in the distance a feeling that it was good. That
it was welcoming. That it was significant.
But he did not know how to get there. He tried to shed the leftover dream,
gathering his schoolwork and preparing for the day. School seemed a little
different today. The classes were the same: language and communications;
commerce and industry; science and technology; civil procedures in
government. But during the breaks for recreation periods and the midday meal,
the other new TW were a buzz with descriptions of their first day of
training. All of them talked at once, interrupting each other, hastily making
the required apology for interrupting, then forgetting again in the excitement
of describing the new experiences. Jonas listened. He was very aware of his own
admonition not to discuss his training.
But it would have been impossible, anyway.
There was no way to describe to his friends what he had experienced there in
the Annex room. How could you describe a sled without describing a hill in
snow; and how could you describe a hill in snow to someone who had never felt
height or wind or that feathery, magical cold? Even trained for years as they all
had been in precision of language, what words could you use which
would give another the experience of sunshine? So it was easy for Jonas to be
still and to listen.
After school hours he rode again beside Fiona to the House of the
Old. "I looked for you yesterday," she told him, "so we could ride home together. Your
bike was still there, and I waited for a little while. But it was getting late, so
I went home." "I apologize for making you wait Jonah said. "I accept your apology," she replied
automatically. "I stayed a little longer than I expected," Jonas explained. She
pedal forward silently, and he knew that she expected him to tell her why. She
expected him to describe his first day of training to ask would have fallen into the category of
rudess You've been doing so many volunteer hours with the Old Jonah said,
changing the subject. "There won't be much you don't already
know." "Oh, there's lots to learn F replied there is administrative work, and the
dietary rules, and punishment for disobedience— —did you know that they use
a discipline wand on the Old, the same as for small children? And there's
occupational therapy, and recreational activities, and medications, and—" They
reached the building and break their bikes. "I really think I'll like it better
than school," Fiona confessed. "Me too," Jonas agreed, wheeling his bike into its
place. She waited for a second, as if, again, she expected him to go on and she
looked at her watch wave D and hurried toward the entrance Jonah stood for a moment beside
his bike, startled. It had happened again: the thing that he thought of now as "seeing
beyond." This time it had been Fiona who had undergone that fleeting indescribable
change. As he looked up and toward her going through the door, it happened; she
changed. Actually, Jonas thought, trying to recreate it in his mind, it wasn't Fiona
in her entirety seemed to be just her hair. And just for that flickering
instant. He ran through it in his mind was clearly beginning to happen more
often. First, the apple a few weeks before.
The next time had been the faces in the audience at the Auditorium, just two days
ago. Now, today, Fiona's hair. Frowning, Jonas walked toward the Annex. I will ask
The Giver, he decided.
The old man looked up, smiling, when Jonas entered the room. He was already seated
beside the table he seemed more energetic today, slightly renewed, and glad to see
Jonas. "Welcome," he said. "We must get started and You're one minute late." "I
apologize Jonas began, and then stopped, flustered, remembering there were to be
no apologies. He removed his tunic and went to the bed. "I'm one minute late because
something happened," he explained. "And I'd like to ask you about it, if you don't
mind." "You may ask me anything." Jonas tried to sort it out in
his mind so that he could explain it clearly. "I think it's what you call seeing Beyond he
said. The Giver nodded. "Describe it," he said. Jonas told him about the experience
with the apple. Then the moment on the stage, when he had looked out and seen
the same phenomenon in the faces of the crowd. "Then today, just now, outside, it
happened with my friend Fiona. She herself didn't change, exactly. But
something about her changed for a second.
Her hair looked different; but not in its shape, not in its
length. I can't quite—" Jonas paused, frustrated by his inability to grasp and
describe exactly what had occurred. Finally he simply said, "It
changed. I I don't know how, or why. "That's why I was 1 minute late," he concluded, and
looked questioningly at The Giver. To his surprise, the old man asked
him a question which seemed unrelated to the scene Beyond When I gave you the memory
yesterday, the first one, the ride on the sled, did you look around?" Jonas
nodded. "Yes," he said, "but the stuff— —I mean
the snow— —in the air made it hard to see anything." "Did you look at the the
sled?" Jonas thought back. "No. I only felt it under me. I
dreamed of it last night, too. But I don't remember seeing the sled in my dream,
either. Just feeling it." The Giver seemed to be thinking. "When I was observing you, before
the selection, I perceived that you probably had the capacity, and what you
described confirms that. It happens somewhat differently to me," The Giver
told him. "When I was just your age— —about to become the new Receiver— —I began to
experience it, though it took a different form. With me it was well, I won't
describe that now; you wouldn't understand it yet. "But I think I can
guess how it's happening with you. Let me just make a little test, to confirm my guess. Lie
down." Jonas lay on the bed again with his hands at his sides you felt comfortable
here now. He closed his eyes and waited for the familiar feel of The Giver's
hands on his back. But it didn't come.
Instead, The Giver instructed him, "Call back the memory of the ride on the sled.
Just the beginning of it, where you're at the top of the hill, before the slide
starts. And this time looked down at the sled." Jonas was puzzled. He opened his
eyes. "Excuse me," he asked politely, "but don't you have to give me the memory?"
"It's your memory, now, It's not mine to experience any longer. I gave it
away." "But how can I call it back?" "You can remember last year, or the
year that you were a Seven, or a Five, can't you?" "Of course." "It's much the same.
Everyone in the community has one generation memories like those. But now
you'll be able to go back farther. Try.
Just concentrate."
Jonas closed his eyes again. He took a deep breath and sought the sled and the
hill and the snow in his consciousness. There they were, with no
effort. He was again sitting in that whirling world of snowflakes at top the
hill. Jonas grinned with delight, and blew his own steamy breath into
view. Then, as he had been instructed, he looked down. He saw his own hands, furred
again with snow, holding the rope. He saw his legs, and moved them
aside for a glimpse of the sled beneath. Dumbfounded, he stared at it. This
time it was not a fleeting impression. This time the sled had— —and
continued to have, as he blinked, and stared at it again— —that same mysterious
quality that the apple had had so briefly. And Fiona's hair. The sled did not change. It simply
was— —whatever the thing was. Jonas opened his eyes and was still
on the bed. The Giver was watching him curiously. "Yes," Jonas said slowly. "I saw it, in the
sled." "Let me try one more thing. Look over there, to the bookcase. Do you see the
very top row of books, the ones behind the table, on the top
shelf Jonah sought them with his eyes. He stared at them, and they changed.
But the change was fleeting. It slipped away the next instant. "It happened," Jonas
said. "It happened to the books, but it went away again." "I'm right, then," The Giver said.
"You're beginning to see the color red." "The what?" The Giver
sighed. "How to explain this? Once, back in the time of the memories, everything had
a shape and size, the way things still do, but they also had a quality called
color. "There were a lot of colors, and one of them was called red. That's the one
you are starting to see. Your friend Fiona has red hair— —quite distinctive,
actually; I've noticed it before. When you mentioned Fiona's hair,
it was the clue that told me you were probably beginning to see the color
red." "And the faces of the people? The ones I saw at the Ceremony?"
The Giver shook his head. "No, flesh isn't red. But it has red tones in it. There was
a time, actually— —you'll see this in the memories later— —when flesh was many
different colors. That was before we went to Sameness. Today flesh is all the same, and
what you saw was the red tones. Probably when you saw the faces
take on color it wasn't as deep or vibrant as the apple, or your friend's hair."
The Giver chuckled, suddenly. "We've never completely mastered Sameness. I suppose
the genetic scientists are still hard at work trying to work the kinks out. Hair
like Fiona must drive them crazy." Jonas listened, trying hard to
comprehend. "And the sled?" he said. "It had the same thing: the color red. But it
didn't change, Giver. It just was. "Because it's a memory from the time when color was.
"It was so— —oh, I wish language were more precise! The red was so
beautiful!" The Giver nodded. "It is." "Do you see it all the
time?" "I see all of them. All the colors." "Will I?" "Of course. When you receive the
memories. You have the capacity to see beyond. You'll gain wisdom, then, along
with colors. And lots more." Jonas wasn't interested, just then, in wisdom. It was
the colors that fascinated him. "Why can't everyone see them? Why did colors
disappear?" The Giver shrugged. "Our people made that choice a choice to go to
Sameness. Before my time, before the previous time, back and back and
back. We relinquished color when we relinquished sunshine and did away with differences."
He thought for a moment. "We gained control of many things. But we had to let go of
others." "We shouldn't have Jonah said fiercely. The Giver looked startled the
certainty of Jonas's reaction. Then he smiled riy You've come very quickly to that
conclusion," he said took me many years.
Maybe your wisdom will come much more quickly than mine."
He glanced at the wall clock. "Lie back down, now. We have so much to
do give her Jonas asked as he arranged himself again on the bed, "how did it
happen to you when you were becoming The Receiver? You said that the scene Beyond
happened to you, but not the same way." The hands came to his
back. "Another day," The Giver said gently.
"I'll tell you another day but Now we must work.
And I've thought of a way to help you with the concept of
color. "Close your eyes and be still, now.
I'm going to give you a memory of a rainbow
[Music]